Guide to the William Hugh McFarlane George Mason University history collection, 1949-1977
George Mason University Libraries
Special Collections and Archives, George Mason University
William Hugh McFarlane George Mason University history collection
1949-1977
George Mason University. Special Collections and Archives.
McFarlane, William Hugh
C0045
6.75 linear feet (6 boxes)
The collection consists of documents and original research done by Dr. McFarlane on the early history of George Mason University. The collection comprises correspondence, newsclippings, reports, meeting minutes, speeches, and audiotape interviews.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Donated by Robert Hawkes in 1998.
Biographical Information
William Hugh McFarlane, educator and administrator, had worked in higher education for nearly three decades when he retired from George Mason University in 1986. Born in Chicago, McFarlane was a pilot in the Army Air Corps during World War II, and then, after the war, entered the University of Virginia on the G.I. Bill. Later, while completing his Ph.D. at the University of Virginia, he worked as student aid director, assistant professor of humanities, and briefly, as the director in charge of fundraising for the Virginia Foundation of Independent Colleges. After receiving his Ph.D. in 1957, McFarlane accepted the position of Director of the State Council of Higher Education, in Richmond, which he held for six years. From 1964-1967 he directed the Virginia Associated Research Center where he organized and managed a university consortium administering NASA's Space Radiation Effects Laboratory at Langley Field, Virginia. Then, in 1968, McFarlane began his eighteen-year career at George Mason University where he was chairman of the Department of Philosophy and Religious Studies from 1968-1979.
Scope and Content
The collection consists of documents and original research done by Dr. McFarlane on the early history of George Mason University. The collection comprises correspondence, newsclippings, reports, meeting minutes, speeches, and audiotape interviews.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged by subject.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Material
Special Collections and Archives also holds the George Mason University archives.
Index Terms
Corporate Names:
George Mason University.
Subjects:
Education, Higher--Virginia.
Document Types:
Sound recordings.
Contents List
- William Hugh McFarlane George Mason University history collection
  - Research (Folder 1, Box 1)
  - Thematic Summary (Folder 2, Box 1)
  - Partial Manuscript (Folder 3, Box 1)
  - Overviews (Folder 4, Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous (Folder 5, Box 1)
  - Significant material (Folder 6, Box 1)
  - 1949 (Folder 7, Box 1)
  - 1950 (Folder 8, Box 1)
  - Important material from the 1954-46 VALC study 1954 (Folder 9, Box 1)
  - Advisory Council minutes 1954 (Folder 10, Box 1)
  - Advisory Council 1955 (Folder 11, Box 1)
  - 1956 (January - June) 1956 (Folder 12, Box 1)
  - 1956 (July - December) 1956 (Folder 13, Box 1)
  - 1957 (January - October) 1957 (Folder 14, Box 1)
  - 1957 (November - December) 1957 (Folder 15, Box 1)
  - C. Harrison Mann's political views in mid-1957) 1957 (Folder 16, Box 1)
  - 1958 (January - February) 1958 (Folder 17, Box 1)
  - 1958 (March - October) 1958 (Folder 18, Box 1)
  - Farr Property 1958 (Folder 19, Box 1)
  - C. Harrison Mann, Jr. biographical sketch (Folder 20, Box 1)
  - C. Harrison Mann history of GMU 1949 (Folder 21, Box 1)
  - 1959 1959 (Folder 22, Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous (Folder 23, Box 1)
  - Some early 1960s (Folder 24, Box 1)
  - Talks - Mr. Finley (Folder 25, Box 1)
  - 1960 1960 (Folder 26, Box 1)
  - 1961 1961 (Folder 27, Box 1)
  - 1962 1962 (Folder 28, Box 1)
  - 1963 1963 (Folder 29, Box 1)
  - 1964 (may - June) 1964 (Folder 30, Box 1)
  - 1964 (July - December) 1964 (Folder 31, Box 1)
  - 1965(January-May) 1965 (Folder 33, Box 1)
  - 1965(June-November) 1965 (Folder 33, Box 1)
  - Important news stories 1965 (Folder 34, Box 1)
  - Minutes/active reading 1965 (Folder 35, Box 1)
  - Newsclippings (Folder 38, Box 1)
  - 1966 1965 (Folder 39, Box 1)
  - Summary of 1964-66 material (Folder 40, Box 1)
  - Petition to the Board of Visitors of the University of Virginia on behalf of Dr. Lee Potter, Dr. Joseph Harrison, Dr.Fanny-Fern Davis, Dr.Linda Grant DePauw, Mrs. Yveline Bretschneider, Mrs. Kosara Gavrilovic, 3/9/66 3/9/66 (Folder 1, Box 2)
  - President Edgar F. Shannon, Jr. correspondence 5/1960-5/31/1965 (Folder 2, Box 2)
  - President Edgar F. Shannon, Jr. correspondence 6/1965-8/31/1966 (Folder 3, Box 2)
  - Joseph L. Vaughan correspondence 1960 (Folder 5, Box 2)
  - Joseph L. Vaughan correspondence 1962 (Folder 6, Box 2)
  - J.N.G. Finley-Joseph L.Vaughan correspondence 1960 (Folder 7, Box 2)
  - Joseph L. Vaughan correspondence 1963 (Folder 8, Box 2)
  - Joseph L. Vaughan correspondence 1963 (Folder 9, Box 2)
  - Robert H.Reid-Joseph L. Vaughan correspondence 1963 (Folder 8, Box 2)
  - Joseph L. Vaughan correspondence 1965 (Folder 11, Box 2)
  - Board of Control 1961 (Folder 12, Box 2)
  - Minutes/active reading 1968 (Folder 13-14, Box 2)
  - The Shea affair 1967 (Folder 15, Box 2)
  - Advisory Committee meeting minutes 11/1968-8/31/1969 (Folder 16, Box 2)
  - William H.McFarlane speeches 1960s (Folder 17, Box 2)
  - Criticism of Lorin A. Thompson 1970 (Folder 18, Box 2)
  - Civil Right case 1/1971-4/30/1971 (Folder 19, Box 2)
  - Civil Right case 5/1971-7/31/1971 (Folder 20, Box 2)
  - Civil Right case 8/1971-3/31/1972 (Folder 21, Box 2)
  - Civil Right Commission charges on racial discrimination 1971 (Folder 22-23, Box 2)
  - Board of Visitors meeting minutes 5/1972-11/30/1972 (Folder 24, Box 2)
  - Board of Visitors meeting minutes 1973 (Folder 25, Box 2)
  - Board of Visitors meeting minutes 1974 (Folder 26, Box 2)
  - Board of Visitors meeting minutes 1975 (Folder 27, Box 2)
  - Board of Visitors meeting minutes 1976 (Folder 28, Box 2)
  - Board of Visitors meeting minutes 1977 (Folder 29, Box 2)
  - Board of Visitors meeting minutes 1978 (Folder 30, Box 2)
  - Board of Visitors meeting minutes 1979 (Folder 31, Box 2)
  - Board of Visitors meeting minutes 1980 (Folder 1, Box 3)
  - Board of Visitors meeting minutes 1981 (Folder 2, Box 3)
  - Board of Visitors meeting minutes 1983 (Folder 3, Box 3)
  - Board of Visitors meeting minutes 1984 (Folder 4, Box 3)
  - Board of Visitors meeting minutes 1985 (Folder 5, Box 3)
  - Board of Visitors meeting minutes 1988 (Folder 6, Box 3)
  - Address of William M. Tuck, Governor (incomplete) 1950 (Folder 3, Box 3)
  - Inaugural address of John S. Battle, Governor (incomplete) 1950 (Folder 8, Box 3)
  - Higher education in Virginia - Report of the Virginia Advisory Legislative Council 1951 (Folder 9, Box 3)
  - Student aid programs in state-supported colleges 1951 (Folder 10, Box 3)
  - Address of John S. Battle, Governor 1/9/1952 (Folder 11, Box 3)
  - Address of John S. Battle, Governor 1/13/1954 (Folder 12, Box 3)
  - Inaugural address of Thomas B.Stanley 1/20/1954 (Folder 13, Box 3)
  - The cost of education in the state-supported colleges 1955 (Folder 14, Box 3)
  - The crisis in higher education in Virginia and a solution 1955 (Folder 15, Box 3)
  - Education of scientists, engineers and other specialists 1957 (Folder 16, Box 3)
  - Address of Thomas B. Stanley, Governor 1/8/1958 (Folder 17, Box 3)
  - Inaugural address of J.Lindsay Almond, Jr., Governor 1/11/1958 (Folder 18, Box 3)
  - Address of J. Lindsay Almond, Jr., Governor 1/28/1959 (Folder 19, Box 3)
  - Virginia Education Facilities Committee-report of the Committee 1959 (Folder 20, Box 3)
  - Higher education in Virginia and its cost to the taxpayer and student 1959 (Folder 21, Box 3)
  - Address of J. Lindsay Almond, Jr., Governor 1/13/1960 (Folder 22, Box 3)
  - Virginia schools in the space age - a continued evaluation of the curriculum, teacher training, and related matters 1961 (Folder 23, Box 3)
  - A report from the State Council of Higher Education to the Governor and the General Assembly of Virginia made pursuant to the House Joint Resolution 74 of the 1960 General Assembly 1962 (Folder 24, Box 3)
  - Address of J. Lindsay Almond, Jr., Governor 1/10/1962 (Folder 25, Box 3)
  - Inaugural address of Albertis S. Harrison, Jr., Governor 1/13/1962 (Folder 26, Box 3)
  - Address of Albertis S. Harrison, Jr., Governor 1/15/1962 (Folder 27, Box 3)
  - Address of Albertis S. Harrison, Jr., Governor 11/30/1964 (Folder 28, Box 3)
  - Address of Albertis S. Harrison, Jr., Governor 1/12/1966 (Folder 29, Box 3)
  - Inaugural address of Mills E. Godwin, Jr., Governor 1/15/1966 (Folder 30, Box 3)
  - Address of Mills E. Godwin, Jr., Governor 1/17/1966 (Folder 31, Box 3)
  - Status of women-Report of the Commission on the Status of Women 1966 (Folder 32, Box 3)
  - Mason Gazette 1995 (Folder 33, Box 3)
  - Legal releases-deed of gift 1/15/1966 (Folder 34, Box 3)
  - Biographical information-interviewees (Folder 35, Box 3)
  - Arthur Arundel interview source material (Folder 36, Box 3)
  - Ralph Baxter interview [1991?] (Folder 37, Box 3)
  - Leon E. Boothe interview 6/17/1991 (Folder 38, Box 3)
  - Weldon Cooper interview 10/23/1987 (Folder 39, Box 3)
  - Dr. J. Wade Gilley interview 1/28/1991 (Folder 40, Box 3)
  - Joseph Harrison interview 12/1987 (Folder 41, Box 3)
  - Senator Omer L. Hirst interview 4/7/1987 (Folder 42, Box 3)
  - Patrick Larkin interview n.d. (Folder 43, Box 3)
  - Edgar A. Prichard interview n.d. (Folder 44, Box 3)
  - Edgar A. Prichard interview 4/8/1987 (Folder 45, Box 3)
  - Edgar F. Shannon, Jr. interview 12/10/1987 (Folder 46, Box 3)
  - Edgar F. Shannon, Jr. interview 4/21/1988 (Folder 47, Box 3)
  - Vincent Shea interview 5/28/1987 (Folder 48, Box 3)
  - Lorin A. Thompson interview 5/28/1987 (Folder 49-50, Box 3)
  - Lorin A. Thompson interview 10/22/1987 (Folder 51-52, Box 3)
  - Lorin A. Thompson and John C. Wood interview 11/12/1980 (Folder 53, Box 3)
  - John C. Wood interview 3/10/1987 (Folder 54, Box 3)
  - John C. Wood, Edgar A.Prichard, and Stacy Sherwood interview 9/16/1989 (Folder 55, Box 3)
  - Anniversary material 9/15/1989 (Folder 56, Box 3)
  - George Mason statue project 10/20/1992 (Folder 57, Box 3)
  - Cecile Bolton Finley-Painting of John Norville Gibson Finley (Folder 58, Box 3)
  - Center for Professional Development-A brief history (Folder 59, Box 3)
  - Growing pains: capital outlay needs of the Virginia state colleges and universities (Folder 60, Box 3)
  - Higher education in Virginia, 1955-65, by Lorin A. Thompson (Folder 61, Box 3)
  - Virginia's crisis in education 5/13/1965 (Folder 62, Box 3)
  - Financing Virginia's future 1966 (Folder 63, Box 3)
  - A regional university of Northern Virginia 1968-75 11/29/1967 (Folder 64, Box 3)
  - Education plan of George Mason College of the University of Virginia 1/1968 (Folder 65, Box 3)
  - Financial needs of George Mason College of the University of Virginia 5/6/1969 (Folder 66, Box 3)
  - Guidebook of organization,policies, and procedures 1971 (Folder 67, Box 3)
  - George Mason University annual report 1972 (Folder 68, Box 3)
  - Financial needs of George Mason College of the University of Virginia 5/24/1971 (Folder 69, Box 3)
  - 1974-76 Budget Advisory Board tour-Governor's Advisory Board 5/21/1973 (Folder 70, Box 3)
  - The strategic plan summary-George Mason University 1977 (Folder 71, Box 3)
  - The Virginia plan for higher education: a progress report 1977 (Folder 72, Box 3)
  - Metropolitan universities, Vol.1 Nos.2-4 (Folder 73-75, Box 3)
  - Diskettes of interviews with Joseph Harrison, Senator Omer Hirst, edgar F. Shannon, Elizabeth Campbel, Vincent Shea, Weldon Cooper, Lorin A. Thompson, Edgar A. Prichard, John C. Wood, Stacy Sherwood, 1964-64 GMC faculty-51/4" diskettes, Wordstar (Folder 76, Box 3)
  - Interview with John C. Wood 3/10/1987 (Box 4)
  - Interview with Edmond & Elizabeth Campbell 4/7/1987 (Box 4)
  - Interview with Omer L.Hirst 4/7/1987 (Box 4)
  - Interview with Edgar A. Prichard 4/8/1987 (Box 4)
  - Interview with Lorin A. Thompson 5/28/1987 (Box 4)
  - Interview with Vincent Shea & Lorin A. Thompson 5/28/1987 (Box 4)
  - Interview with Lorin A. Thompson 10/22/1987 (Box 4)
  - Interview with Lorin A. Thompson 10/23/1987 (Box 4)
  - Interview with Weldon Cooper 10/23/1987 (Box 5)
  - Interview with Joseph Harrison 10/29/1987 (Box 5)
  - Interview with Hugo Blankenship 11/19/1987 (Box 5)
  - Interview with Edgar F. Shannon, Jr. 12/10/1987 (Box 5)
  - Interview with Edgar F. Shannon, Jr. 4/21/1988 (Box 5)
  - Interview with Joseph Harrison 4/25/1988 (Box 5)
  - Interview with Cecile Bolton Finley 4/28/1988 (Box 5)
  - Interview with Arthur Arundel 11/1988 (Box 5)
  - Introduction by William H. with Joseph Harrison 9/1989 (Box 5)
  - Interview with 1964-65 faculty: Lee H. Potter, McFarlane Interview Richard H. Pierce, Harry C. Stutts, John G. Hartley, James R. Health 9/16/1989 (Box 6)
  - Interview with Edgar A. Prichard, John C. Wood, and Stacy Sherwood 9/16/1989 (Box 6)
  - Interview with Lee H. Potter, Joseph Harrison 9/17/1989 (Box 6)
  - Interview with Patricia R. Plante, President, University of Southern Maine 7/13/1990 (Box 6)
  - Interview with John "Til" Hazel 10/30/1990 (Box 6)
  - Interview with Edgar A. Prichard and [J. Wade Gilley?] 1/28/1991 (Box 6)
  - Interview with Edgar A. Prichard [1991] (Box 6)
  - Interview with J. Wade Gilley 1/31/1991 (Box 6)
  - Interview with Leon Boothe 6/17/1991 (Box 6)
  - Interview with Ralph Baxter 6/19/1991 (Box 6)